"How Much Exercise Does It Take
to Improve Aging Cognitive Function?"
Based on a meta-analysis
of 20 studies,
mental performance
may be improved
with even modest weight loss
among overweight individuals,
though that may be due
not to the weight loss per se,
but rather
the prescribed exercise.
For example, one study
randomized obese elders
to one of four groups
for a year:
a weight-loss diet alone,
exercise without weight loss,
both, or neither.
Compared to the control group
that did neither,
global cognition improved
in all the three other groups,
but while weight loss
and exercise
beat out weight loss alone,
weight loss and exercise
didn't beat the exercise alone,
suggesting that exercise is
the most potent component.
The American College
of Sports Medicine
cites meta-analyses of dozens
of prospective studies
following tens of thousands
of people for years
that suggest
that those who are active
have a 38 percent lower risk
of cognitive decline
and a 39 percent lower risk
of developing
Alzheimer's disease.
And, apparently,
the more, the better.
Every extra 500 calories
expended a week
appears to correlate
with an additional
ten percent drop
in dementia risk.
However, even light
physical activity,
such as low-intensity walking,
or how yoga and tai chi
are often practiced
by older adults,
has been associated
with at least
some sort of cognitive gain
in about half of the studies
done to date.
If the relationship
between exercise
and dementia prevention
is cause and effect,
as much as 20 percent
of all cases
of Alzheimer's disease
in Western countries
may be attributable
to physical inactivity.
That would mean more than
a million cases of Alzheimer's
just in the U.S. alone.
As with all observational data,
though,
there's the potential
for confounding
or reverse causation.
Maybe there's a shared factor
causing both,
such as atherosclerosis,
contributing to both inactivity
and dementia,
or maybe those
genetically predisposed
to exercise a lot
also have a more robust
cognitive reserve
(though a Mendelian
randomization study
failed to find this).
Instead of inactivity
leading to dementia,
dementia could lead
to inactivity.
Prospective studies
following people over time
can show that the inactivity
does precede the dementia,
but both mental
and physical activity
can start declining
years before a diagnosis.
When researchers looked closely
at the data,
only inactivity
less than 10 years
before the diagnosis
was associated with dementia,
suggesting the causality
may indeed be backward.
When put to the test,
interventional trials show
physical activity
can be increased
in dementia patients,
which can improve
physical fitness,
but disappointingly did not
slow cognitive impairment.
Perhaps, we're just not
catching people early enough?
Adults with either
normal cognition
or mild cognitive impairment
randomized to exercise training
tend to improve
their cognition
compared to those ending up
in the less active
control groups.
A slight majority of studies
that concurrently tracked
brain imaging
found those randomized
to exercise
experienced a beneficial effect
on overall brain volume
as well as specifically
the hippocampus,
a part of the brain
that plays a critical role
in memory formation
and for which atrophy predicts
memory decline and dementia.
The seminal study,
"Exercise training
increases size of hippocampus
and improves memory,"
randomized older adults
to either a year
of supervised moderate
aerobic exercise (walking)
or a control group,
which instead involved a year
of stretching
and toning classes.
On average,
the hippocampus volume
of those in the control group
shrank 1.4 percent,
which is consistent
with the one to two percent
annual shrinkage
typical of old age.
In contrast,
over that same year
in the walking group,
their hippocampus volume
increased two percent,
which is like adding
a year or two of brain volume
(though may subsequently shrink
back to baseline
in as few as six weeks
of inactivity;
so you got to keep it up).
A similar study
that added a third group-
a resistance training arm-
found a similar
aerobic training reversal
of age-related shrinkage
in the memory centers
compared to the balance
and toning control group,
but unfortunately
there was no benefit seen
in the nonaerobic
strength-training group.
It's unclear exactly which type
of exercise is best,
but the cognitive benefit
of aerobic training
appears to be larger
than resistance training.
In most of the randomized
controlled trials
of older adults,
walking was the most frequently
chosen mode of exercise.
The best volume, duration,
frequency, or intensity
is also unknown.
Based on a meta-analysis
of nearly a hundred
randomized controlled trials,
more important
than session duration,
weekly frequency,
program duration, or intensity,
may be total training time.
However studies spliced it up,
it appeared to take exercising
for a total
of at least 52 hours
before a cognitive benefit
can be established.